<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata version="1.0">
  <uniqueid id="org.sil.fonts.lateeflight.1.285" />
  <vendor name="SIL International" url="http://www.sil.org/" />
  <credits>
    <credit
      name="Bob Hallissy, Jonathan Kew"
      url="http://software.sil.org/lateef/"
      role="SIL designers and font engineers"
    />
    <credit
      name="Peter Martin"
      url="http://software.sil.org/lateef/"
      role="SIL designer"
    />
  </credits>
  <description>
    <text lang="en">
      Lateef is named after Shah Abdul Lateef Bhitai, the famous Sindhi
      mystic and poet. It is intended to be an appropriate style for use
      in Sindhi and other languages of the South Asian region.
      
      This release supports virtually all of the Unicode 5.0 Arabic character
      repertoire (excluding the Arabic Presentation Forms blocks, which are not
      recommended for normal use). A few Arabic script characters that were added
      to Unicode 5.1, 6.0, 6.1, and 7.0 have also been included. Font smarts are implemented using Graphite
      technology.
      
      This font uses state-of-the-art OpenType and Graphite font technologies,
      including variant glyphs for a number of characters for use in particular
      contexts.
      
      This font provides a simplified rendering of Arabic script, using basic
      connecting glyphs but not including a wide variety of additional ligatures
      or contextual alternates (only the required lam-alef ligatures). This
      simplified style is often preferred for clarity, especially in non-Arabic
      languages, but may be considered unattractive in more traditional and
      literate communities.
      
      Two fonts from this typeface family are included:
      
      * Lateef Regular
      * Lateef Bold
      
      The Latin glyphs in this font are from the Crimson Pro font family
      (https://github.com/Fonthausen/CrimsonPro).
      
      For detailed documentation see the contents of the 'documentation' folder.
      
      Known Issues (v 1.280 alpha)
      ----------------------------
      - Combining marks above or below composite characters may not position correctly
      (e.g. If a character has nuktas above, the combining mark above may not position
      properly. If a character has nuktas below, the combining mark BELOW may not
      position properly.)
      - When text is kashida-justified in Word, the lam/alef ligature may break
      - This version of the font does not have kerning (where characters may touch each
      other), so there is no need to report when a reh touches the following character, etc.
      - This version of the font has not had the linespacing values evaluated, so there is
      no need to report vertical linespacing issues.
      
      ChangeLog
      ---------
      (This should list both major and minor changes, most recent first.)
      2020-12-16 (SIL WSTech team) Lateef Version 1.280 (alpha release)
      - Incorporated both OpenType and Graphite in the same font
      - Added Lateef Bold
      - Changed design of all Latin glyphs to use Crimson Pro
      - Updated Latin script repertoire to support "Recommended characters for Non-Roman fonts"
      https://scriptsource.org/entry/gg5wm9hhd3
      - Added U+204F and U+2E41 for Sindhi language support
      - Added Arabic characters: U+0600..U+0605, U+0609..U+060B, U+060D..U+0613, U+0615..U+061A, U+0620,
      U+063B..U+063C, U+063E..U+063F, U+065F, U+0773..U+077F, U=08BE..U+08C2, U+08C7
      - Redesign of some Arabic digits
      - Redesign of hook on heh-goal
      - Redesigned nuktas and variants to be more calligraphic and less geometric
      - Redesigned head of feh, qaf, waw
      - Redesigned U+06C5 for Kyrgyz language and added feature cv51, Kyrgyz OE,
      supporting the bar design
      - Redesigned U+0677 and U+06C7
      - Redesigned high hamza characters (U+0674..U+0678)
      - Harmonized design of many characters so that all characters in that family (eg seen, dal, feh, keheh, etc) would be consistent
      - Harmonized design of all terminals
      - Harmonized vertical stems
      - Harmonized design of small v and inverted small v characters (U+063D, U+065A,
      U+065B, U+0692, U+06B5, U+06C9, U+06CE, U+06EE, U+06EF, U+06FF, U+0756,
      U+0769, U+077E, U+08B2, U+08BE..U+08C2)
      - Harmonized design of punctuation used in Arabic script
      - Changed scaling for some quranic marks (combining) and adjusted weights
      - Revised side-bearings for many glyphs
      - Made space and nobreak space have the same width
      - Changed width of kashida
      - Many adjustments to position of anchors
      - Changed position of above nukat on U+06AD and U+06AC
      - Changed design of U+FDF2 (Allah) to include alef
      - Implemented new Allah ligature rules
      - Implemented support for UNICODE ARABIC MARK RENDERING (UTR #53)
      - Added UI name strings for Graphite and OpenType features
      - Removed support for Sindhi-style heh when Sindhi language is selected
      - Removed support for Urdu-style heh when Urdu language is selected
      - Removed "Arabic U" feature
      - Removed "Show invisible characters" feature
      - Removed "Jeh hack" feature
      - Removed "Dotless head of Khah hack" feature
      - Added "Yeh hamza" feature for Kyrgyz language
      - Added Kyrgyz language support in Graphite and OpenType
      - Added Rohingya language support in Graphite and OpenType
      - Added support for Comma downward when Sindhi language is selected
      - Fixed End-of-Ayah rendering in OpenType
      
      2017-03-23 (SIL NRSI team) LateefGR Version 1.200
      - Removed U+03BC
      - Added U+061C, U+063D, U+076E..U+0772, U+08AA, U+08B2, U+2012, U+2015,
      U+2027..U+2029, U+202F, U+2066..U+2069
      - Added alternates for End of Ayah (U+06DD) and changed default design
      - Design changes to U+0755, U+0756, U+075A
      - Design changes to U+06AC and U+06AD
      - Design changes to U+06DF..U+06E1 (to follow http://unicode.org/review/pr-73.html)
      - U+06BA is now dotless in all positions
      - U+00A0 advanced width changed to match U+0020
      - Size of dagger alef (U+0670) is reduced above U+0678
      - Added Graphite language tags
      - Added Graphite features
      - Added Graphite Kerning for reh-like and waw-like characters
      - Linespacing is looser
      - Does not include OpenType support
      
      2008-11-06 (SIL NRSI team) Lateef Version 1.001
      - Re-released under OFL
      - no other changes from 1.0
      
      2005-06-03 (SIL NRSI team) Lateef Version 1.0
      - First public version
      - Released under the SIL Freeware License
    </text>
  </description>
  <license url="http://scripts.sil.org/OFL" id="org.sil.ofl.1.1">
    <text lang="en">
      Copyright (c) 1994-2021, SIL International (http://www.sil.org/).
      
      This Font Software is licensed under the SIL Open Font License, Version 1.1, with Reserved Font Names "Lateef" and "SIL". This license is copied below, and is also available with an FAQ at: http://scripts.sil.org/OFL
      
      ----------------------------------------------------
      SIL OPEN FONT LICENSE Version 1.1 - 26 February 2007
      ----------------------------------------------------
      
      PREAMBLE
      The goals of the Open Font License (OFL) are to stimulate worldwide development of collaborative font projects, to support the font creation efforts of academic and linguistic communities, and to provide a free and open framework in which fonts may be shared and improved in partnership with others.
      
      The OFL allows the licensed fonts to be used, studied, modified and redistributed freely as long as they are not sold by themselves. The fonts, including any derivative works, can be bundled, embedded, redistributed and/or sold with any software provided that any reserved names are not used by derivative works. The fonts and derivatives, however, cannot be released under any other type of license. The requirement for fonts to remain under this license does not apply to any document created using the fonts or their derivatives.
      
      DEFINITIONS
      "Font Software" refers to the set of files released by the Copyright Holder(s) under this license and clearly marked as such. This may include source files, build scripts and documentation.
      
      "Reserved Font Name" refers to any names specified as such after the copyright statement(s).
      
      "Original Version" refers to the collection of Font Software components as distributed by the Copyright Holder(s).
      
      "Modified Version" refers to any derivative made by adding to, deleting, or substituting -- in part or in whole -- any of the components of the Original Version, by changing formats or by porting the Font Software to a new environment.
      
      "Author" refers to any designer, engineer, programmer, technical writer or other person who contributed to the Font Software.
      
      PERMISSION &amp; CONDITIONS
      Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy of the Font Software, to use, study, copy, merge, embed, modify, redistribute, and sell modified and unmodified copies of the Font Software, subject to the following conditions:
      
      1) Neither the Font Software nor any of its individual components, in Original or Modified Versions, may be sold by itself.
      
      2) Original or Modified Versions of the Font Software may be bundled, redistributed and/or sold with any software, provided that each copy contains the above copyright notice and this license. These can be included either as stand-alone text files, human-readable headers or in the appropriate machine-readable metadata fields within text or binary files as long as those fields can be easily viewed by the user.
      
      3) No Modified Version of the Font Software may use the Reserved Font Name(s) unless explicit written permission is granted by the corresponding Copyright Holder. This restriction only applies to the primary font name as presented to the users.
      
      4) The name(s) of the Copyright Holder(s) or the Author(s) of the Font Software shall not be used to promote, endorse or advertise any Modified Version, except to acknowledge the contribution(s) of the Copyright Holder(s) and the Author(s) or with their explicit written permission.
      
      5) The Font Software, modified or unmodified, in part or in whole, must be distributed entirely under this license, and must not be distributed under any other license. The requirement for fonts to remain under this license does not apply to any document created using the Font Software.
      
      TERMINATION
      This license becomes null and void if any of the above conditions are not met.
      
      DISCLAIMER
      THE FONT SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT OF COPYRIGHT, PATENT, TRADEMARK, OR OTHER RIGHT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, INCLUDING ANY GENERAL, SPECIAL, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF THE USE OR INABILITY TO USE THE FONT SOFTWARE OR FROM OTHER DEALINGS IN THE FONT SOFTWARE.
    </text>
  </license>
  <copyright>
    <text lang="en">
      Copyright (c) 1994-2021 SIL International.
    </text>
  </copyright>
  <trademark>
    <text lang="en">"Lateef" and "SIL" are trademarks of SIL International</text>
  </trademark>
</metadata>